<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A petition to the lords to examine the religion and cariage of D. Ban. Archb. By Hugh Broughton</title>
            <author>Broughton, Hugh, 1549-1612.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1608</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 11 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A16997</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 3878</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S119310</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99854517</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99854517</idno>
            <idno type="VID">19943</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A16997)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 19943)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1196:11)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A petition to the lords to examine the religion and cariage of D. Ban. Archb. By Hugh Broughton</title>
                  <author>Broughton, Hugh, 1549-1612.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 14 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>G. Thorp?],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Amsterdam? :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Ano 1608.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Place of publication and printer suggested by STC.</note>
                  <note>D. Ban. Arch. = Richard Bancroft.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Union Theological Seminary (New York, N.Y.). Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bancroft, Richard, 1544-1610.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:19943:1"/>
            <p>A PETITION TO THE LORDS, TO examine the religion and cariage of D. Ban. Archb.</p>
            <p>By <hi>Hugh Broughton.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>An<hi rend="sup">o</hi> 1608.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:19943:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:19943:2"/>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Wrote a reply (right honourable) vpon a Iew in defence of all Chriſte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome: as many of your Lordſhips have ſeen the book. The Iew being ſubtile had caught D. Brancroft, as an allower of our works in Iudaiſme with him. Wherin art could give no better an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer then that our old notes were long agoe revoked. The ſcholers of Geneva were alſo in Iudaiſme: But the Senatours gave me leave to confute them: &amp; ſware that they would bridle them for ever. Then they went about to have me killed for denying that Q. E. ever meant to defeat K. I. In contradictio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Beza wrot to Baſil to D. Polanus. I ſayd all was but a dreame: and I would hav printed an Ebrewes Ebrew co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendation of the Q. for her royall
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:19943:3"/>purpoſe in ſending me word by Sir Iulius Caeſar that I ſhould choſe my eccleſiaſtical preferment for my co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentaries vpon Daniel. But Ban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>croft by 3000. wel given to a cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tier and a Lady, procured grief to Q. Eliſabet and defeatance. This commendation allowed by the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate: One Grinetus &amp; Pinot now dead, and another now dead hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered with diſturbance ſtrange: that the Senate ſent me word of danger by ſoldiers ſtirring. That I record. Bancroft ſeing himſelf in Iudaiſme: and as I heard in his al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed Libel equall ſcoffer as of a miſt ſoone ſcattered, raved againſt me, for pearles to ſuch, and holy things to ſuch. Now ſeing the Law of God which may not paſſe contemned biddeth reprove open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly them that ſin openly, I require
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:19943:3"/>from God that your Lordſhips hear with juſtice my articles againſt Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chard Bancroft.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Iudaiſme. Article 1.</label>
               <lb/>
Rabbi Farar objected that our S. Luke ſet not downe our Lords kinred but Ioſephs, and citeth our Engliſh tranſlation: and our notes further, to prove extremitie of do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Bancrofts Iudaiſme.</label>
               <lb/>
Bancroft railed againſt a right defence: and ſuffreth our Athean notes of treaſon againſt the Goſpel.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Therfore</label>
               <lb/>
Bancroft is equal in Athean vila<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie with the Iew.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:19943:4"/>
               <label>Article II.</label>
               <lb/>
A weightier cauſe cannot be fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d then y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> of our Lords houſe after the fleſh: &amp; right diſtinction of ending Salomons race in Iechonias. The Iewes vniverſally denied that: &amp; Bancroft in allowing our ban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned croft of notes, &amp; raving againſt the defender of the right, helpeth him.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Therfore</label>
               <lb/>
Bancroft is in equal Iudaiſme:</p>
            <p>
               <label>Article III.</label>
Rabbi Farar vrged this true pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition, that by Bancrofts aſſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion he might ban all the holy croft of our Goſpel.</p>
            <p>Yf the Romanes be the legges of Daniels Image, or be the fourth beaſt, whom Daniel bringeth to pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:19943:4"/>before the redeemer commeth into the world, our Goſpel hath miſſed of the true redeemer. For Chriſt our L. came into the world the firſt day that in Bethleem taxe over the world argued the Romans a full deſtruction of the double Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedonians (who in deed are the two legges and fourth beaſt).</p>
            <p>
               <label>Bancrofts treaſon to the Goſpel.</label>
               <lb/>
The Romanes in his allowed notes be the Images leggs &amp; fourth beaſt.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Therefore</label>
               <lb/>
A croft of bane or poiſon is in Bancrofts banned Iudaiſme.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Article IV.</label>
               <lb/>
The glory of all the old teſtame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:19943:5"/>prophecied in Levit. 26. hath hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie Dan. 9. the covenant of God re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membranced and expounded: that the holy Angel telled the moſt gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious Prophet how the 70. yeares captivity ſpace ſeven times, 490 yeres, are fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Daniels prayer to our Lords death, ending Moſes Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies. And all the New teſtame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t is diſturbed by the diſturbance of this.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Rabbi Farar and Barbinel.</label>
               <lb/>
Lively is allowed by Bancroft to make 590. y.: ſo that Ezra whoſe Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther was killed 2 King. 25. two and fiftie before Babel fell, and ſaw the Perſians end at Livelies 230. ſhould live 280 yeres &amp; ten Zorobabelidae ſhould draw 557. yeres, <note place="margin">Math. 1.</note> that both teſtame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts ſhould be nothing worth:</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:19943:5"/>
And Bancroft in the libel allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Lively, as Bar-Lo, denyeth ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice ended at our Lords death, or time of his Birth
<list>
                  <item>Baptiſme</item>
                  <item>Death</item>
               </list> told in the law</p>
            <p>
               <label>Therfore</label>
               <lb/>
Bancroft is to be holden an aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant to the vnbeleeving Iewes, &amp; equall in Athean vilany, againſt our hope of ſalvation.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Article V.</label>
               <lb/>
Rabbi Farar buſily beſtirreth him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf to prove that by our graunt our ſcripture is not pure in text: ſo it ſhould not be a rule of ſalvation.</p>
            <p>Ba<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>croft as Bar-Lo allowing Liue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:19943:6"/>damning the old teſtame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t in 848 readings of text as corrupted would perſwade that we blaſpheme the old teſtament juſtly: &amp; accuſe in notes and tranſlation Act. 7. the N. T. to be corrupt,</p>
            <p>
               <label>Therfore</label>
               <lb/>
Bancroft is a deadly enemy to both teſtaments, and vnallowable in this courſe to be a teacher: or to rule in Lerning.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Article VI.</label>
               <lb/>
Farar, or old Ben Arama.</p>
            <p>They who ſayd Jeſus their Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our went to Hell cannot holding that, hold Salvation.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Proof from Law &amp; Goſpel.</label>
               <lb/>
Moſes <hi>Levit.</hi> 26. and all Rabbines
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:19943:6"/>vpon him, &amp; in all their writings: and our Goſpel and S. Paul &amp; Luke Act. 7. ſhew that all faithful go one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to heaven.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Therfore</label>
               <lb/>
Bancroft is to be banned with all the croft of his Athean vilanie of his hereſie and railing againſt Archb. Whitgift &amp; Doctor Bilſon for this ſyllogiſme:</p>
            <p>The place which received our Lords ſoul gone from the body and this world is haides of the Crede: and the deſcending is the paſſage thither: Whitgift and all Grecians.</p>
            <p>Paradiſe is the place vnto which our Lords ſoule, or all holy ſoules went hence. Doctor Bilſon &amp; both teſtaments all Iewes for the juſt: and the beſt Chriſtian Graecians &amp; hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:19943:7"/>then in their kind.</p>
            <p>Therfore to deſcend to Hell in the Creed is to go vp to Paradiſe.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Concluſion.</label>
               <lb/>
So Bancroft in the conſent to the Libel hoping to ſee his countrey on flame raving againſt the BB. Syllo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſme ſhewed all extremitie of any Iudaiſme to overthrow the mayn poinct of ſalvation.</p>
            <p>How the Creed ſhould be tranſlated:</p>
            <p>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> meaneth, To go hence to God: &amp; becauſe Gods throne is on high, and there the godly have heaven, &amp; the wicked, Hell: in the holy it is: a going to Heaven: in the other, to Hell. The
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:19943:7"/>vnlearned wight that ſeing this mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſo explaned would mainteyn a dayly Lie, that our Lords ſoule, went down, wher al aſcend to God, and went to Hel, not (by the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel) to heaven, this vnlearned wight ſhould be removed from his place. And D. Whitgift wel held that al who deny our Lords ſoule to have removed to Haides ar in Atheiſme: as denyers of ſoules immortalitie. And this much for Iudaiſme. The Machmadean abſurdities ſold as with the Bible, told to the K. for ſome part: yf B. Ban not all the croft of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, I wil give him in Greek Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles quiet advertriſeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t: Although his G. vnderſtandeth Greek as I do Perſian: yet for the ſimple I would not openly ſhew his errors &amp; others may turn all to Engliſh for his Grek. Touching harme to me for the K. I
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:19943:8"/>blame none but four ſcholers of Geneva, Bancroft &amp; Bar-Lo. Ban<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>croft brent theſe words as treaſon: <hi>The K. of our Language.</hi> He can rendre no other reaſon, why he brent the book vnder Q. E. and K. I. your Lordſhips may aſk him. For the doctrine the D. cannot blame one ſyllable. Therfore his firſt hatred to the K. bred the ſecond. D. Vahan ſaw his danger: and went about to calme al. Now Bar-Lo would not have ſcoffed the Biſhops ſyllogiſme and me, befooling himſelf, but to ſet his countrey as Nero on a flame. So for the K. the Biſhops and I were ſcoffed. Further neyther nation nor perſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> do I accuſe for any harm, to any. My Petition for the Iewes vnto the K. is not for my ſelf, but for the Biſhops if they be able: and I could wiſh D. Bancr. all grace of
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:19943:8"/>ſufficiency in Thalmudiques and Greek: to honour Chriſtendome in this ſort for the gayn with the Pain. And all the world muſt bear me re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord how frendly D. Bilſon is ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noured: whoſe wordes I take to prove againſt Iewes by ſcripture &amp; Greeks that our Lords ſoule aſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded from the croſſe alone into hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven: as the ſecond time in the body. So I would honour all the reſt: and give good leave to ech one to ſtep before me: to the gain and Pain. It is well known that the Iew meant to foile all Chriſtendome: as that none ſhould match him in elegancy of Talmudiques: and propounded ſuch a ſcope to have the N. Teſt: compared with Moſes 613 lawes, as ſufficie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t without the Thalmud, that he litle looked for any to be found ever in the world, that would ſhew
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:19943:9"/>the Apoſtles to be the beſt Thalmu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diques. Now none that know the greatnes of this paines: &amp; how hard it is to find tranſlaters from Ebrew into other tongues, that all nations; may ſee how the matter is caried: and what payn wilbe to find ebrew written works: &amp; Greeks to be tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlated into Ebrew: as all Polychro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nius vpon Daniel none of ſkil wil here ſhew wil with deſire to preve<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t others. And it would be an honour to our nation, yf an Archbiſhop or Biſhop ſhould paſſe Rabbines and match Greeks in their kind: as Cra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer by Martyrdome and Iewel by fathers are an eternal honour to our Iland. And if the Biſhops wil not move the K. the P. and your ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours wil: and wiſh the Biſhops far ſager and quieter cariage.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Lordſhips moſt humble <hi>Hugh Broughton</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
